<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - Judith Midgley</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/authors/judith-midgley</link>
 <description>Associate: Pilotlight SDS
</description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Living Well with SDS : Our Work So Far</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/living-well-sds-our-work-so-far</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;An  illustration of the prototype resources we have developed&quot; title=&quot;Living Well Prototype Resources&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;1&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/Living%20Well%20Prototypes.png&quot; width=&quot;1076&quot; height=&quot;505&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following an initial six month research, awareness raising and recruitment phase, we have facilitated seven day-long co-design workshops. The workshops have brought together people with lived experience of younger onset dementia, their carers, social workers, community psychiatric nurses, practitioners, private sector support providers and providers of independent advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workshops have covered the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workshop 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to know one another; Finding out about Pilotlight and co-design; Thinking about how we want to work together; Learning about self-directed support – values and principles; Action Research&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workshop 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recap on Workshop; Signing off our Working Together Agreement; Learning more about self-directed support and the 4 options; South Ayrshire Market Place - local supports; Research Analysis; Barriers and opportunities self-directed support offers for Living Well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workshop 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recap on Workshops 1 and 2; Developing our Pilotlight Characters; Designing journeys for our Pilotlight Characters; Hearing some self-directed support stories from Ayrshire Independent Living Network; Discussing and agreeing the themes emerging from our research&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workshop 4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recap on Workshop 3; Thinking about what good information looks like; Starting work on our theme 1: Information; Starting work on our theme 2: Clear pathway; Hearing some more self-directed support stories&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workshop 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recap on Workshop 4; Starting to develop our South Ayrshire Community Asset map; Continuing work on our theme 1: Information; Hearing about the South Ayrshire Health and Social Care Partnership’s Dementia Review; Continuing working on our theme 2: Clear pathway&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workshop 6&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recap on Workshop 5; Reviewing our South Ayrshire Community Asset Map and webpage and agreeing next steps; Reviewing our Post Diagnostic Support work and agreeing next steps; Starting work on our theme 3: Bespoke Support; Hearing about new developments with carers and self-directed support; Starting work on our theme 4: Support for Carers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workshop 7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recap on Workshop 6; Refining our post diagnostic support work, Dementia Toolkit and webpage; Continuing work on our theme 3:  Bespoke Support; Hearing more about support for carers in South Ayrshire; Continuing work on our theme 4: Support for Carers; Planning for our final workshop on 8th December&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the 8th December we will be holding our final workshop in which we will be reviewing our ideas and prototype resources. These include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dementia Toolkit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post Dementia Support Visit Letters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;South Ayrshire Council Dementia Web Pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning and Development for Community Psychiatric Nurses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carer Support Planning Toolkit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key learning points and links to these resources will be available on the website in the New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 11:30:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">182 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/living-well-sds-our-work-so-far#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>SDS Test Budgets for Substance Misuse Recovery</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/sds-test-budgets-substance-misuse-recovery</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Test budget planning&quot; title=&quot;Test budget planning&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/test-budget-planning.jpg&quot; width=&quot;2000&quot; height=&quot;1500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Pilotlight SDS for substance misuse recovery pathway we are working with people with lived experience, providers and commissioners to understand how self-directed support could be used to improve support by raising awareness and understanding of self-directed support, as well as confidence and capacity to take greater control of the design and delivery of support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key strand of phase 1 of this work has been the provision of test budgets to the co-design team members with lived experience. As we could not find any examples of people in Scotland using self-directed support for substance misuse recovery, we thought it important to test out how small amounts of money might be used. Before joining the co-design team, members with lived experience were advised that they would be entitled to a test budget of up to £800, based on £100 per workshop attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second of the eight workshops we introduced the recovery outcomes and asked co-design team members with lived experience to pair up with practitioners to have a conversation about which recovery outcomes they wanted to focus on. Some pairs also started to discuss ideas for how the test budget could be spent to progress towards the identified recovery outcome/s and record this on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/resources/test-budgets-substance-misuse-recovery&quot;&gt;the straightforward paperwork&lt;/a&gt;. This planning activity continued at the third workshop. We started paying out the test budgets from this workshop onwards. Test budget recipients were able to control the pace at which they accrued and then claimed the money. All chose to ‘save up’ until they had the amount required for the item or support identified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At each subsequent workshop test budget recipients worked with the practitioners to have a conversation and record the progress they were making in spending their test budgets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So what were the recovery outcomes that people chose to focus on and how did they use their budgets?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Person A&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recovery Outcomes :&lt;/strong&gt; Alcohol and drugs, Relationships, Mental and emotional wellbeing, Occupying time and fulfilling goals, Housing and independent living and Money matters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test Budget Use :&lt;/strong&gt; £300 for one year’s internet, £250 for a 100 hour long TEFL internet teaching course and £250 for interview clothes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasons :&lt;/strong&gt; Stay in touch with friends and family, Online SMART recovery, TESLA course online, Clothes for interview&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Person B&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recovery Outcomes : &lt;/strong&gt;Occupying time and fulfilling goals, Children - maintain contact with daughter&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test Budget Use :&lt;/strong&gt; Provisional driving license £56, Driving theory test £35 x 3, Block driving course £580, Bus fares to and from Aberdeen £12 x 3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasons :&lt;/strong&gt; “It will change my life if I could drive and I have more employment opportunities”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Person C&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recovery Outcomes :&lt;/strong&gt; Mental health - negative thinking, stress, smoking, Spiritual growth - inner peace, Education - study&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test Budget Use :&lt;/strong&gt; Travel to Plus Carden Abbey for retreat £28 + £50 donation, Laptop £300, Printer, Hypnotherapy and counselling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasons :&lt;/strong&gt; Develop IT skills. SMART recovery training. College home study course “I tried hynotherapy session but felt it was too expensive and not for me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Person D&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recovery Outcomes &lt;/strong&gt;: Relationships, Fulfilling Goals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test Budget Use :&lt;/strong&gt; Laptop £400, One year broadband £216, Highway Code £2.50, Theory test £23, Car driving £62&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasons :&lt;/strong&gt; “Having broadband would really help me to learn before getting a job.Having a landline would really help me to stay in touch with family.”Increased employment opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Person E&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recovery Outcomes :&lt;/strong&gt; Occupying time, Self-care - Eye test leading to new glasses, Mental and emotional wellbeing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test Budget Use :&lt;/strong&gt; Car tax £151, Fuel £30, MOT £55, Eye test and new spectacles, New battery £114&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasons :&lt;/strong&gt; “Due to the test budget I have over recent months been able to put my car on the road for the first time in two years. This permits freedom to attend various meetings/ courses that would otherwise be very difficult due to rural transport. Reduces isolation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2016 15:32:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">175 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/sds-test-budgets-substance-misuse-recovery#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>SDS for Substance Misuse Recovery : Our Work So Far</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/sds-substance-misuse-recovery-our-work-so-far</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Image of taking more control&quot; title=&quot;Taking More Control&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/Website%20image.png&quot; width=&quot;1069&quot; height=&quot;858&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Following an initial six month research and recruitment phase, we have facilitated 5 day-long co-design workshops which have brought together people with lived experience of substance misuse recovery and practitioners from Grampian Health Board, Aberdeenshire Council and 4 voluntary sector providers (Turning Point Scotland, Cair Scotland, Drugs Action and Aberdeen Foyer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are using the Design Council &#039;Double Diamond&#039; design methodology to explore the barriers and opportunities that self-directed support presents for people in recovery for substance misuse and to design solutions and new products to address these. The workshops have also been designed to prepare co-design team members with lived experience to be ready to apply for the two peer support worker posts that will be integral to phase 2 of this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workshops have covered the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workshop 1: Getting to know one another, thinking about recovery, finding out about Pilotlight and co-design, thinking about how we want to work together, learning about self-directed support (values and principles) and action research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workshop 2 : Finalising Working Together Agreement, more about self-directed support  (4 options) and recovery (barriers and opportunities), test budgets – beginning to plan using recovery outcomes, peer supporter roles, research feedback, designing Pilotlight characters (fictitional people in recovery form substance misuse) for use in design activities).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workshop 3 : Introducing our Pilotlight characters, self-directed support case study from Hampshire, designing self-directed support for our Pilotlight characters, agreeing our working themes, test budgets – continuing to plan, discussion about peer support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workshop 4 :  Beginning work on theme 1 (SDS and the recovery journey) and 2 (Maximising outcomes), test budgets – feedback on initial spend and continuing to plan, guest speakers from Turning Point Scotland on peer support work and starting to develop the peer support worker role description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workshop 5 : Completing work on theme 1 (SDS and the recovery journey) and 2 (Maximising outcomes), test budgets – feedback on progress and continuing to plan, peer support workers : employee and employer expectations, peer support workers :  designing interview questions, specimen answers and practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the next workshop on 28th April we will begin working on our third and fourth themes - &#039;Positive risk taking&#039; and &#039;Personal approach by providers&#039;&#039;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2016 14:44:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">155 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/sds-substance-misuse-recovery-our-work-so-far#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Using SDS to set up and run a small business: The Zealand Family</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/using-sds-set-and-run-small-business-zealand-family</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Zealand family photo montage&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-web-3x2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/styles/web_3x2/public/media/PL2-Alex_DxOPsp.jpg?itok=hQa3ffLc&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our third Pilotlight pathway we are working with a co-design team of people who deliver and access support in Moray to look at how self-directed support can be used for small business development.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	Right from the start, co-design team members have been eager to hear real stories from people who have pioneered using self-directed support in this way.  At our second workshop Alex, Barbara and Paul Zealand came to talk to us and to answer questions about how they had used self-directed support to set up and run Alex’s handyman business.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	Alex has a handyman/odd jobs business. He provides a range of services to older and disabled people in Buckie, including lawn mowing, window cleaning, patio cleaning, fence painting and garden furniture sanding and treatment. Alex loves what he does, especially the lawn mowing. He is very popular with his clients, many of whom look forward to his visits and to having a cup of tea and a chat with him.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	Alex’s mother Barbara explained that Alex had been due to leave school last summer and start college. A couple of months before he was due to start, Alex told her he did not want to go to college.  So they had to act both creatively and quickly because they did not want Alex to go to the day centre full time (he goes one day a week in order to keep up with his network of friends from school).&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	They applied for a direct payment (one of the self-directed support options). In this option the Council pays you an amount of money (based on an assessment of your needs) and you (or someone acting on your behalf) choose and arrange your support services. Barbara and Alex decided to spend Alex’s direct payment on employing three support workers (also known as personal assistants) to support him to run a handyman business. They could also have applied for a grant to purchase the specialist equipment Alex uses in his business (rechargeable strimmer and lawnmower) but due to the short time they had to set up, they went ahead and bought this themselves.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	Barbara and Alex recruited his support team with help from the Direct Payments worker at Moray Council, who put their advert into the Job Centre. They recruited Paul, Willie and Tracy. They were not necessarily looking for people with experience of care work, but for people with the right attitudes who Alex liked and got on well with. Recruiting their own staff gave them control. One of the staff they recruited is a joiner and is passing on some skills to Alex.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	Barbara told us that the SDS assessment process was very easy. They have a payroll company who works out all the tax and national insurance, but they pay the staff themselves.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	At the moment Alex is on Employment Support Allowance. This means he can earn up to £20 per week after all his business expenses have been paid before he loses any benefit. Alex’s charges for his services are lower than other businesses to keep his earnings below this amount. The long term goal is for him to come off Employment Support Allowance.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	From starting with three clients through his church network, Alex now has 15 clients and a waiting list. Alex has friends who are currently at the day centre who would like the opportunity of having or being part of a small business. Barbara has approached the day centre to offer them the opportunity for someone to come and work with Alex but so far they have not taken this up. As Barbara explained, this is not an easy option, being an employer can seem very scary and she cannot make it happen for everyone, but it is has been the right thing for Alex.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	Barbara left us with three very inspiring messages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Try It!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t be afraid of failing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can change it as you go along&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2014 11:42:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">120 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/using-sds-set-and-run-small-business-zealand-family#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Working in Co-design Teams</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/working-co-design-teams</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Card - I want to speak&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-web-3x2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/styles/web_3x2/public/media/PL2-co-design-team_2.jpg?itok=TtcyYrYL&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pilotlight is a project about co-designing pathways to self-directed support for groups of people who have so far been less engaged with the self-directed support agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Co-design can be defined as, &lt;em&gt;“the process of designing with people that will use or deliver a product or service.”&lt;/em&gt; (UK Design Council). Co-design may be seen as the first step in co-production, &lt;em&gt;“which means delivering public services in an equal and reciprocal relationship between professionals, people using services, their families and their neighbours. Where activities are co-produced in this way, both services and neighbourhoods become far more effective agents of change.”&lt;/em&gt; (NESTA)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been working in co-design teams in Moray and the Scottish Borders throughout the two Pilotlight pathways since January 2013. In this blog post we want to talk about the way we work and some of the benefits of working in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a key principle of service design (the design approach being used throughout Pilotlight) we are using co-design to help us to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Deeply understand the barriers to accessing self-directed support for people with mental health problems in Moray and for people who require support with decision making in the Scottish Borders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design solutions to these barriers to increase the capacity of support providers and people using the services to deliver self-directed support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Pilotlight co-design teams include people who use and deliver services. In Moray, the co-design team has helped us to conduct action research within their local community and practitioner groups and identify key barriers to people with mental health problems accessing self-directed support. We are now beginning to develop solutions with the group. Some of the creative tools we have used include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Asking co-design team members to find and present examples of effective information design (in any media) to the group, from which the team identified the components of good information design.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Considering a general leaflet about self-directed support to identify how it could be enhanced to address the specific information needs of people with mental health problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asking each co-design team member to develop a ‘persona’ or character profile of someone who has lived experience of mental health problems or of a mental health practitioner and then developing these characters together for use in designing solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building scenarios to identify where and how information about self-directed support should be provided.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engaging in role plays to identify how the generic SDS assessment process needs to be tailored for people with mental health problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key to the success of co-design in Pilotlight is working from the basis that experiences of service users are of equal value to the knowledge and experience of professionals who deliver services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this basis, we spent time at the beginning of the project developing values and principles to guide us all in undertaking our Pilotlight work. These have been informed by the principles set out in the Scottish Government’s self-directed support strategy, which are based on a human rights approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through using creative tools and designing our workshops to be as engaging and innovative as possible, we also hope to build co-design facilitation skills within the local authorities and provider organisations who we are working with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideas of Professor Edgar Cahn are an inspiration to us. We think this video explains why co-production is worth doing. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;media-youtube-video media-element file-default media-youtube-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&quot;media-youtube-player&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;390&quot; title=&quot;No more throw away people&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/egav5xjb-lg?wmode=opaque&amp;amp;controls=&amp;amp;rel=0&quot; name=&quot;No more throw away people&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; id=&quot;No more throw away people&quot;&gt;Video of No more throw away people&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-field-photo-credit field--type-text field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;* Photography by Margaret Adams, member of Moray co-design team.&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 12:12:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">126 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/working-co-design-teams#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>We&#039;re nearing the end of our ‘Discover’ phase...</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/were-nearing-end-our-discover-phase</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our last blog we talked about how we intended working with the co-design teams in Moray and the Scottish Borders. We have now held workshops with both teams. We are nearing the end of our ‘Discover’ (research) phase of the pathway in Moray and part of the way through this phase in the Scottish Borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Moray we are working on the theme of ‘Access to self-directed support for people with mental health problems’. We have eight people who access mental health services and one unpaid carer, along with practitioners from social work, health promotion and service providers, on the co-design team. We held the first workshop with the people who access services and the unpaid carer. We felt we needed to give them the same opportunities the practitioners had already had to find out more about Pilotlight and decide whether they wanted to participate before bringing the whole co-design team together. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the first workshop we looked at:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Well-being &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An introduction to Pilotlight and self-directed support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lived experiences of mental health problems &amp;amp; services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparation for participatory action research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feedback on the day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also had a lunch to which we invited the practitioner members of the co-design team. Everyone who came along was asked to bring a physical object that represented something that keeps them well. We asked everyone to introduce themselves and tell us about their object. People brought along a whole range of objects, including motorcycle gloves, welly boots, mobile phones, and a log. But by far the most popular object was a photograph of a pet cat or dog. These featured much more frequently than photographs of partners or children! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone went away from the first work shop equipped with interview schedules, recording equipment and cameras to do some research into mental health awareness in Moray. They then presented their findings to the whole co-design team at the second workshop. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key findings were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Many people didn’t know very much about mental health services in Moray unless they were already using them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lack of understanding and knowledge about mental health came across strongly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generally people were unsure as to how they would access services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most people would speak to their GP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internet and leaflets were the most common information sources mentioned&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a lack of information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a lot of stigma associated with mental health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the second workshop we identified the barriers to access to self-directed support for people with mental health problems, but also the opportunities it offers. These included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Flexibility, Choice – of service, worker, location&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to plan ahead&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More and different opportunities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try new things out. Purchase service for a trial period.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More control : building self-confidence and self-esteem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creativity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most effective services will flourish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opportunities for micro enterprises&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Short term solutions for short term problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opportunities for individuals to pool their budgets &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help people who want something else or who have fallen through the cracks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do away with service monopolies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the third workshop we will be deciding which of the barriers we want to focus on designing solutions for. Already identified is the need for information specific to people with mental health problems. Everyone went away from the second workshop with research assignment : to find one or more pieces of effective information. We await the ‘show and tell’ session at the workshop next week with anticipation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 12:06:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">125 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/were-nearing-end-our-discover-phase#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The first meeting with Pilotlight’s Provider Network</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/first-meeting-pilotlights-provider-network</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday 3rd October we met 25 support providers from across Scotland at the Scottish Youth Theatre venue, Glasgow. The day was the first meeting of the Pilotlight Provider Network and was a great success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We invited a mix of providers from the voluntary and private sector alongside local authority providers to join our network for the duration of the Pilotlight project. They will provide assurance on the evidence emerging from the pathways, ideas on solving challenges, information on barriers and share examples of good practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At our first meeting, we asked some big questions including, &lt;strong&gt;‘what does self-directed support mean to you and your organisation?’&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;‘what is your organisation currently doing around self-directed support?’&lt;/strong&gt;. Also, &lt;strong&gt;‘what are the barriers to delivering self-directed support?’&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;‘what are your organisation doing to overcome these barriers?’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These questions generated a lot of great discussion and revealed some really valuable insight for the Pilotlight project and also the individual pathways. Some of the key areas of insight were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Culturally, the move to self-directed support for providers is presenting many barriers around language and understanding. Simple solutions like a glossary of terms would be useful for providers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a need for planning time and clarity around who will lead support planning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting the balance between choice and risk right is a concern and was a common theme which emerged from the providers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensuring that self-directed support is outcomes focused. There is a fear that at a local authority level, inputs and outputs are the focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More transparency about planning and strategy is required from local authorities. There is also a need for more co-production by providers and the people using services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are barriers around finance, contracting and commissioning including block contracting and how this will be affected, the nature of contracting requires change and some provider frameworks aren’t user friendly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A general requirement for more information; in the marketplace and also for people and families to get information about their options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also asked the support providers to help us analyse our research frameworks which will be used throughout the ‘Discover’ phase of Pilotlight. With their help, we interrogated the questions we will ask people using services, local authorities, commissioners and support providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our next meeting with the Provider Network will be in February 2013 and we are already looking forward to presenting our Pilotlight research back to them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2012 12:39:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">133 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/first-meeting-pilotlights-provider-network#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
