<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - SDs and self employment</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/tags/sds-and-self-employment</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>SDS for Small Business</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sds-small-business</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;h2&gt;SDS for Small Business: Key Learning Points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;SDS can be used to support people to set up small businesses. &lt;a href=&quot;/resources/count-me-video&quot;&gt;Count Me In video&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/resources/count-me-campaign&quot;&gt;Count Me In campaign&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-employment can be a good option for people with fluctuating conditions. &lt;a href=&quot;/resources/count-me-video&quot;&gt;Count Me In video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self worth, use of skills and talents, well-being, and making a contribution are greater motivating factors than making money for many people using their SDS for small business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As this is a new and innovative use of SDS, local authority commissioners need to be proactive in helping everyone see the possibilities and to invest in a development officer resource. &lt;a href=&quot;/resources/count-me-video&quot;&gt;Count Me In video&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/resources/count-me-campaign&quot;&gt;Count Me In campaign&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mainstream business support services and tools are not well suited to SDS for small business. Bespoke tools and support services are needed. &lt;a href=&quot;/resources/accessible-roadmap-and-guide-starting-and-sustaining-small-businesses-using-sds&quot;&gt;Accessible Roadmap and Guide resource for starting and sustaining small businesses using SDS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear of losing benefits and confusion about complex benefit rules can prevent people exploring the small business option. &lt;a href=&quot;/resources/benefits-and-small-business-case-studies&quot;&gt;Benefits and small business case studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peer support through a local network can help people develop and sustain their businesses. The Pilotlight co-design process was an effective catalyst for the development of a network. A local development officer has been key to sustaining it. &lt;a href=&quot;/resources/moray-small-business-network&quot;&gt;Moray Small Business Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 11:41:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">193 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sds-small-business#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
