<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - Tracey Stewart</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/authors/tracey-stewart</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>My Experience of Pilotlight</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/my-experience-pilotlight</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title=&quot;Pilotlight Themes&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/SM_theme%20overview.jpg&quot; width=&quot;3082&quot; height=&quot;1988&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;Back in September 2015, I was told about a course called Pilotlight which would be running in Aberdeen and was briefly told it was about recovery and there would be people in recovery from alcohol and drug misuse and practitioners and we would be discussing and working together to see if there was any improvements in the process of recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my first day I was very nervous and wasn&#039;t sure that this was for me but I managed to get myself there and thankfully it wasn&#039;t an early start. When I arrived, everyone was very welcoming. I could see that the rest of the people like myself were also just as nervous as I was. We were introduced to Judith Midgley and Kate Dowling who work for Iriss and they would be facilitating the 8 workshops once a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then had to do a brief introduction of ourselves in order to get to know one another. We then were told that the workshops were about self-directed support for substance misuse recovery and peer support work. Pilotlight has brought together people with lived experience of substance misuse recovery and practitioners from Grampian Health Board, Aberdeenshire Council and 4 voluntary sector providers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Turning Point Scotland, Cair Scotland, Alcohol and Drugs Action, and Aberdeen Foyer.) We were exploring the barriers and opportunities that self-directed support presents for people in recovery. The workshops have been designed to prepare co-design members with lived experience to be ready to apply for two posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I knew it, it was lunch time and the food they served was lovely and plenty of it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After getting through the first day I wasn&#039;t sure that this was for me but I knew I had plenty of time as it was only once a month I had to attend. Before I knew it, the month had flown in and it was time for the second workshop. When I arrived, everyone again was very welcoming but I had noticed we were one member down! We were now starting to get a bit more involved and learning all about self-directed support, peer worker roles and test budgets. Food again was lovely and a few jokes were made about the soup, which made us all relax even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While workshops 3 and 4 were going on, I had a few family problems going on, which made it very difficult to concentrate and felt that I may not be able to continue in the project. I had feelings of being a failure, which then led me to feel very disappointed and very stressed out. As the workshops were now getting more involved with case studies, working themes, test budgets and maximising outcomes. we also had guest speakers and we were continuing to plan for the peer worker roles. I found this very difficult as I had not done anything like this in years and had started to dread the workshops. But I managed to pull myself together and get back into the course learning more and more about self-directed support and peer support work and also writing blog posts for the Pilotlight website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am now at the end of the Pilotlight project with only one more workshop to go. I feel that the peer support roles are not really as well organised as they should be with issues on how long the posts are for, whether the workers will be working on there own or not and kind of feel like we are the guinea pigs for the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this moment I&#039;m not sure wither I will go forward for the job or not but I&#039;m glad I was part of the project and it has opened my eyes and learnt a lot from it and I have also met a lot of nice people through the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2016 15:11:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">170 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/my-experience-pilotlight#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Self-directed Support Peer Support Workers:  What should the employee and employer expect of each other?</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-peer-support-workers-what-should-employee-and-employer-expect-each-other</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Photo of a woman writing&quot; title=&quot;Tracey writing&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/Tracey%20writing%20interview%20questions_0.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our Pilotlight project in Aberdeenshire we are working with people with lived experience, providers and commissioners to understand and co-design how self-directed support could be used to improve support for people in recovery from substance misuse. We are aiming to raise awareness and understanding of self-directed support, as well as confidence and capacity to take greater control of the design and delivery of support. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of phase 1 of the project a pathway and tools will have been produced to enable access to self-directed support for people using substance misuse services. In phase 2 Turning Point Scotland will employ two members of staff as ‘Self-directed Support Peer Support Workers’ to deliver awareness raising and training across Aberdeenshire. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At our fifth of the eight workshops in phase 1 of the project, the Pilotlight co-design team spent some time thinking about what the Self-directed Support Peer Support Workers should be able to expect from their employer and what the employer should expect from them as employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, Tracey Stewart, one of our co-design team members with lived experience, blogs about employer and employee expectations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A peer support worker with lived experience may be new to the job, but they have a lot of experience in addiction in their own lives. They can provide wisdom from their own life experiences and hope that recovery is possible. They must be positive and approachable and show initiative when dealing with individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peer support worker will be involved in on going development and will provide peer support and practical assistance to individuals in order for them to regain control over their lives and their recovery path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They can expect:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Respect as per any worker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They will be involved in an induction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shadowing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On going development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good support network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Equalities policies and practices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarity of purpose and clear objectives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decent terms and conditions e.g. holidays, pay etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Health and safety / Risk assessment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grievance and appeals process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The employer should provide a safe working environment for all members of staff and have written policies and procedures in place. They should provide training and development to enable workers to develop their skills and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expectations of both are very similar and mirror each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The employer can expect that their employee will be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reliable and dependable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Respectful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Able to use their own initiative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skilled at record keeping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accountable for their own actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good communicator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a good sense of humour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledgeable about self-directed support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be willing to undertake a disclosure to obtain a PVG (Protection of Vulnerable Groups) scheme record. Having a criminal record need not exclude a person from peer support work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 12:57:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-peer-support-workers-what-should-employee-and-employer-expect-each-other#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Self-directed Support Peer Support Workers : The Values and Skills Required</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-peer-support-workers-values-and-skills-required</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;wayne and tracey&quot; title=&quot;wayne and tracey&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/wayne-and-tracey.jpg&quot; width=&quot;2000&quot; height=&quot;1796&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The values and skills required to be a peer support worker are firstly and most importantly I think is to have good communication skills and be a good listener. They must have a good knowledge about the subject whether it be alcohol and drug misuse or a mental health issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peer support worker must be open-minded and non judgmental and have empathy, honesty and respect for the individual. They need to provide knowledge, experience,  emotional, social and practical help. Their role includes exploring solutions with the individual and knowing which step to lead the individual to next stage of their recovery.  They should focus on strengths not weaknesses and realise when the individual is ready to move on to their next stage of the recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peer support worker must be positive ,friendly, approachable and show initiative when dealing with the individual and as they have lived experience this can help as they have been in similar situations and have relevant experience but remain as equals but professional at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peer support worker can also benefit by increasing levels of self-esteem, confidence building and a sense of worth and feelings of doing good. Peer supporters can often experience an increase of their own ability to cope with mental health problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 09:23:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-peer-support-workers-values-and-skills-required#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Self-directed Support and the Recovery Outcomes</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-and-recovery-outcomes</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;recovery outcomes checklist&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;1&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/recovery-outcomes_0.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1500&quot; height=&quot;744&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-directed support is Scottish government legislation and aims to give people more choice and control over their care and support services in Scotland. People in recovery from alcohol and drug misuse can get self-directed support but few have it yet.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are eight values and principles to support self-directed support. These are: participation, innovation, risk enablement, responsibility, involvement, informed choice, dignity and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-directed support has many great opportunities for individuals on their path of recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are ten recovery outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Relationships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alcohol &amp;amp; drug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self care and nutrition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical health &amp;amp; wellbeing  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mental &amp;amp; emotional wellbeing &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occupying time &amp;amp; fulfilling goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Housing &amp;amp; independent living&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offending&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Money matters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Children&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals will be offered a planned budget with social worker and council and there are four options:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Council arranged, you can ask the council to arrange your support for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Direct payment, you receive the money and you arrange your support services. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Individual service fund, you can direct your budget,  council or care organization holds the money but you decide  how it is spent,  and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A mix of all options.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The money can be spent on a wide range of things to support a person’s recovery outcomes. For example, passes for travel to get to support cafes in many different areas, swimming, gym or helping with employment and courses, money matters and even help with housing. It helps to support people in a way that suits them in their recovery journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 17:04:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Kate Dowling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">149 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-and-recovery-outcomes#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
