<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - Wayne Gault</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/authors/wayne-gault</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Some Thoughts on Peer Support Work</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/some-thoughts-peer-support-work</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Welcome slide with image of tea and scones&quot; title=&quot;Welcome, Tea and Scones&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/Slide1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; height=&quot;540&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alcohol and Drug Partnerships across Scotland (as well as other areas of the public sector) are going through a learning curve to figure out how best to engage with our communities. I’m going to share our learning over the past few years because this might have some relevance to how our SDS peer support efforts might emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, services think about ‘what’s broken?’ and ‘how can they fix it?’. Services focus on solving problems. For example, health and social care bosses worry about the growth in older people living longer and the consequences for increased health and social care service demand. This is a glass half empty perspective. What stops us focusing also on the glass half full – all that life experience and wisdom, people with time on their hands, many not ready to stop being productive and looking for an opportunity to give something back to their community?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addictions, this distinction is important because people in difficulty are often stigmatised, prejudiced and marginalised. They have little power and voice. It’s well recognised that a key aspect of recovery is about connecting, belonging and having hopes and dreams. We need to focus on what’s strong, not what’s wrong. We need to help people and communities have the power to solve their own problems rather than have a solution imposed on them. Folk don’t want a service. What they really want is a life. Services can be essential to helping gain a good life but they are not sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Aberdeenshire, the Alcohol and Drug Partnership has been quietly supporting the growth of Asset Based Community Development (ABCD) via funding of 3 Community Forums, all now led by community members. Their composition and approach truly reflects partnership working, manifest in the increasing numbers of community members with lived experience of alcohol and other drug issues being active contributors to forum meetings and activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These Forums (or should that be Fora?) have simple objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•      Supporting people in marginalised communities to get involved&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•      Helping community members feel they can influence decisions and have their voices heard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•      Challenge stigma&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•      Shifting the balance of power&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow our twitter feed at @abdnshireadp to find out the specifics of what they’ve achieved. There’s too much to list here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the last few years of growth of the Forums, we’ve learned a lot that may be relevant to the development of the SDS Peer Support worker posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lessons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.      Some services focused on solving problems may not be well suited to ABCD. They might be limited in what they can offer but more importantly, what they offer might actually inhibit much more important community solutions from emerging. That’s ok, as long as such services recognise what they are good at and don’t get in the way of communities developing their own solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.      Services should leave ego at the door. If they are going to help, still give communities and their members the credit for the good stuff that emerges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.      Be persistent and don’t go for easy wins. Staff can get tired of vulnerable folk who don’t turn up and let them down and instead go with the usual suspects who are always reliable. Give folk a chance and recognise great things don’t happen over night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4.      Our role is to help citizens through a long learning curve. Go at the speed of community trust, not at the speed of funding cycles. We’ve seen people go through these stages in their learning or confidence building journey:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;–        No learning. Just do what experts/services say!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;–        Build confidence to critique services. ‘I liked this..., I didn’t like that...’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;–        Recognise the value and power of their own lived experience and use it to come up with their own ideas for projects in their community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;–        Help services to value the power of citizens’ lived experience and help services to come to terms with the shift in power towards communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;–        Feel OK to try stuff knowing that some of it won’t work and be willing and able to reflect, learn and improve for next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5.      Be excited and have fun. People won’t be inspired to be attracted and freely share their time if we’ve taken the joy out of participating. Free tea, coffee, cakes, home-made soup, and oodles of friendship and fun are essential ingredients and the least we can offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 13:11:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">157 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/some-thoughts-peer-support-work#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The opportunities self-directed support could offer for people in recovery from substance misuse Part 2     </title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/opportunities-self-directed-support-could-offer-people-recovery-substance-misuse-part-2</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Image of different types of seating&quot; title=&quot;Different seating options&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/image004.jpg&quot; width=&quot;436&quot; height=&quot;219&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that is immediately attractive about Self Directed Support (SDS) is that it offers new opportunity and choice. For some people, that choice will be getting help from formal services where the individual is the ‘client’ of the service. For others, that choice will not be about being a client but a citizen free to do as they see fit in their community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasingly people in recovery recognise that “a human with all their flaws is more imaginative, adaptable and creative than the most perfect formal service”. SDS can help individuals believe in their own ability to solve problems rather than be dependent on services to solve their problems for them. This is about returning power to the people and SDS has the potential to do just that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully when folk are looking for advice about SDS, they will hear less of: “Hi, my name is xxx; these are my qualifications; what’s the matter with you?” This kind of needs analysis always generates the same answer: “you need our service”! Instead, folk should increasingly hear: “Hi, my name is xxx, what is it that matters to you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many people, services are essential but they are not sufficient. Connecting to family or achieving a sense of purpose and belonging in the community are just as important. People who attend Fellowship meetings will be very familiar of the idea of maintaining their recovery by “giving it away to keep it”. People freely  and willingly acting as sponsors, peer supporters or offering some other kind of service to their community have much better recovery outcomes than those that don’t. Such behaviour carries the message of recovery to the next person. Could SDS help people to do this in their community?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are motivated to do things in their community for different reasons. Which of these could SDS unlock for you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;·         Having a dream (for you, your family or community). How could SDS help you discover your dream and help you move towards it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;·         Being worried about something. How could SDS help you or your community get away from something that concerns you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;·         An opportunity to identify and develop the gifts you already have so you can give them away. How could SDS help you liberate your skills rather than focus on your deficits to enable you to give something back to your community?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;·         Opportunity to connect with people. Everyone needs an opportunity to belong. How could SDS grow your choices of things and people to connect with?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;·         Politics and social justice. Folk in recovery often feel marginalised and unimportant. How could SDS help you take your power back and become active and a strong voice for others who might be struggling in your community?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choice. Let’s see how imaginative, adaptable and creative we can be with the choice offered by SDS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2016 10:56:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/opportunities-self-directed-support-could-offer-people-recovery-substance-misuse-part-2#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The opportunities self-directed support could offer for people in recovery from substance misuse</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/opportunities-self-directed-support-could-offer-people-recovery-substance-misuse</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I liken SDS in addictions to that new pair of running shoes currently sitting in my cupboard unused. Those shoes offer so much potential to improve my life but I’ve yet to overcome the barriers to actually go out for a run. Unless we figure out how to overcome the barriers, there is a risk that SDS might be the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Members of the co-design team at work&quot; title=&quot;Members of the co-design team at work&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;1&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/Wayne%2C%20Bryan%20and%20Tracey%20Test%20Budget.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;717&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;	Aberdeenshire, in keeping with most other areas of Scotland, has been redesigning its services to fit within an integrated overarching ‘recovery oriented system of care’ (ROSC). That simply means that people can quickly access a local service that will help them figure out what their issues are, what help they might need to overcome those issues and organise the help required from appropriate services, free of charge. This recovery planning process aims to customise what’s on offer from existing services according to the needs of the client. However, every person is different and it is possible that the client may have unique needs that the ROSC can’t help with. That’s where I’d hope SDS would kick in: to enable the provision of unique interventions customised to the unique needs of the client that otherwise would be unavailable.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	So in theory, someone could obtain services on healthcare and prescribing, counselling, finance advice and so on sufficient to stabilise a chaotic life. But for long term sustained recovery, those interventions might be insufficient to sustain independent living and full citizenship. The client might uniquely have long standing issues around their sense of self at a spiritual level that could be addressed by developing ‘mindfulness’ skills. Training on mindfulness isn’t available from ADP funded services in Aberdeenshire but this could be bought specifically for the client via SDS.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	That’s the theory at least. SDS holds huge potential to uniquely customise people’s recovery journeys. But there are a range of potential barriers that could get in the way. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;SDS is only available to people who are eligible. Eligibility could change as their ‘risk’ changes. So once someone at risk has achieved stability by accessing readily available ROSC services, their risk profile will have reduced. It is unclear whether this now reduced risk person would still be eligible for SDS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those assessed as having financial means need to pay a contribution to SDS services. People may not actually be able to afford such a financial contribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People may want an SDS intervention that is not available locally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The budget available to invest in an SDS intervention might not be sufficient to buy the required intervention, especially if available council budgets get tighter towards the end of the year as all the money is spent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entitlement to SDS needs to be assessed by the social work department. Some clients may be reluctant to engage with statutory services or go through an eligibility assessment, preferring to seek help from 3rd sector organisations or the NHS free at the point of need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SDS works best where people are confident, assertive and can articulate their needs. Many people with addiction problems may not be able to exert the same control over SDS at the early stages of their recovery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recent experience of a free bus-pass pilot to help folk in recovery engage with supports Aberdeenshire generated negative stigmatising press from some quarters. We could reasonably expect such negative reaction with SDS applied to addictions recovery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m hugely excited about the IRISS Pilotlight addictions SDS project. It aims to co-design ways in which SDS could be used in Aberdeenshire to support and enhance recovery, to develop capacity to use and benefit from SDS, and to identify the system changes required in order to implement SDS here. I hope that the project helps us figure out how to overcome the barriers so that personalisation becomes a reality for all and not just for a minority. If that is possible, then one day I might just get out for that run.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	Wayne Gault&lt;br /&gt;
	Aberdeenshire Alcohol and Drug Partnership&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 13:56:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Kate Dowling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">145 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/opportunities-self-directed-support-could-offer-people-recovery-substance-misuse#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
