<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - Jennifer Ritchie</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/authors/jennifer-ritchie</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>What do mental health professionals need to know about self-directed support? The view from someone with lived experience</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/what-do-mental-health-professionals-need-know-about-self-directed-support-view-someone-lived</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;User goals – join some clubs, i.e. cycling, walking, art&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-web-3x2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/styles/web_3x2/public/media/PL2-outcomes_0.jpg?itok=o6wr84nq&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very difficult question to answer, as it is not so straight forward. I say that because everyone with mental heath issues is an individual. Ideally I would like to suggest that mental health professionals right from the psychiatrists and GPs to hands on care givers know how this new way of delivering social care services and the payment method works (as I see it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to see workshops set up for everyone working in mental health services.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	I would like to see a group of people trained to run these workshops, ideally who have no connection to local councils or working in a social work setting. I say that because I think there needs to be no barriers. They should be aware of mental health, maybe ideally these &#039;trainers&#039; could be carers or people with mental health problems themselves. I would also like to see included in the training, learning about how to deliver a package that would suit the needs of individuals.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	What you teach to a GP or a social worker may be different to what a carer or a family member needs to find out. Where would they get reliable information? Could this take a few weeks or a few months or is there even time to discuss fully how this would impact on a persons life? Also an online support tool would be of use as people could go over it in their own time or to refresh their memory.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	In our Pilotlight workshops I have found out that you need to support each other while learning about self-directed support. This should hopefully continue when mental health professionals are learning about self-directed support. In Stockport they have already had a big trial on how self-directed support could help people like myself. We should be taking their learning and maybe try and better it to work in the Moray area. Or just accept that their report worked and just run with it - as they say,  ‘if it aint broke don&#039;t fix it&#039;.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;br /&gt;
	Understanding of self-directed support seems straight forward, picking up the leaflet that you might find in the library, surgery, support group. People thinking about accessing self-directed support may feel optimistic that this could be a better way of getting a service or they could feel anxious about change. Whether someone is optimistic or anxious, if mental health professionals know about self-directed support and how it works, they can be more reassuring to the person they are supporting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2013 12:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">124 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/what-do-mental-health-professionals-need-know-about-self-directed-support-view-someone-lived#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>My experience of being in a co-design group </title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/my-experience-being-co-design-group</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;co-design work&quot; style=&quot;width: 1024px; height: 685px;&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-web-3x2&quot; data-delta=&quot;1&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/styles/web_3x2/public/media/PL2-DSC_0033.jpg?itok=rWWouPB4&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having never experienced this kind of project before I had no idea what it entailed. I&#039;m involved in Pilotlight in Moray because I wanted to make a difference to other peoples lives (like me) who are living with mental health. I want to try and enable them to manage their health problems, get help easily and when they need extra support, knowing it will be there. Here is my experience of being in the co-design group so far…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found starting out was difficult, ‘breaking the ice’ so to speak. I think the first session was the most difficult. When there are a lot of issues to cover, the many different subjects that have to be discussed, it felt like the mountain was too big to climb. However, this just showed how much we wanted to all be there and for us as a group, how much we wanted to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose a lot of people in the same space fighting for the same thing just takes time to mellow a bit - which it greatly has. After the initial session I was afraid to go on with the project, thinking that I could have voiced my opinions differently. I asked questions like: how was I going to contribute to this group? Was this co design group right for me? Are people’s lives going to get any benefit from this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussion during the third workshop put us all on an equal footing and I felt that I was more part of a group and that we were all heading in the same direction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the separate homework tasks we had to do before workshop 3 (we were asked to bring examples of effective information design) were helping people become aware of mental health issues. Some people brought in examples of effective mental health communication. Thinking of different wording, colors, age appropriate topics i.e. highlighting bullying in schools can be very different from making children aware of self harm. We also looked at where mental health information could be communicated; whether it be on the side of a bus, cereal boxes or posters. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the last workshop, we created character profiles of people who suffer from mental health problems. Our characters will be at the centre of our designs. This task let me see that although you feel isolated during episodes of mental ill health, actually what you can feel can be the same as what another person may be feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also try and get across in my working group that mental health cannot disappear and that having long periods of remission is the best way for me to look at myself and apply it to this co design group. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Role Play of the SDS assessment process has helped us visualise what could happen when a person applying for SDS is put into a situation that they may or may not handle well. This has given us insight to adapt how the assessment process could change for the better. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-field-photo-credit field--type-text field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;* Photography by Margaret Adams, member of Moray co-design team.&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2013 12:27:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">129 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/my-experience-being-co-design-group#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
