<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - M. Steven</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/authors/m-steven</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Self-directed Support and Risk Enablement</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-and-risk-enablement</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Risky activity&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;1&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/Risk_Enablement_0.jpg&quot; width=&quot;527&quot; height=&quot;296&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I am going to focus on self-directed support and risk enablement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January 2013 my then 85 year old aunt was diagnosed with vascular dementia. As increasing numbers of us are aware such news is at the very least depressing, especially when it is accompanied by a &#039;there&#039;s nothing that can be done and she&#039;s only going to get worse&#039; prognosis. Being reluctant to take anyone at face value I thought to myself &#039;we&#039;ll see...&#039; and set about finding out whether anything could be done to help my aunt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out there were indeed several things that could be done to improve my aunt&#039;s condition. In discussion with my aunt we agreed she should discontinue a sleeping pill and one other medication. Several dietary supplements have been instrumental in helping my aunt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, while I have not (yet – never give up!) managed to cure my aunt&#039;s dementia, I have improved and for the moment at least, stabilised her condition. Neither myself nor my aunt wish to see her take any unnecessary backward steps, which brings us to self-directed support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between February 2013 and December 2014 my aunt received 4 visits a day from East Renfrewshire home carers. To a woman these carers were happy to prompt my aunt to take her dietary supplements along with her prescription medication with several of them agreeing that the supplements were helping my aunt. However, in December 2014 after I made a complaint to the home care organiser she retaliated by instructing all of my aunt&#039;s carers to immediately stop prompting her to take her supplements. We were in a pickle!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turned out that for almost 2 years and supposedly unbeknownst to the management team, the carers had been contravening the East Renfrewshire home care medication policy. As the management team were unable to rewrite said policy unless my aunt was willing to give up taking her dietary supplements (which she was not) continuing with East Renfrewshire home care was simply not an option. What were our options then? Precious few seemed to be the answer until a nice lady at the Care Inspectorate told me about self-directed support (as well as the wonderful East Renfrewshire self-directed support Forum). Sure enough self-directed support will indeed return to my aunt the right to take control of her own health again and choose to be reminded to take her dietary supplements which, quite frankly, is a God send!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has not all been plain sailing though. Most service providers I have approached have medication policies almost as inflexible as East Renfrewshire&#039;s. I understand their concerns about being sued should something go wrong, I really do, but surely a way around this could be found? What about having the service user sign a legal waiver each time they were prompted to take their dietary supplements for example? Of the many companies I spoke to I found only 3 who would be willing to prompt my aunt to take her supplements and only on the condition that I obtained a letter of approval from her GP. (This wasn&#039;t very problematic.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to say a few words about the self-directed support concept of risk enablement in relation to dietary supplements (or &#039;non-prescription medication&#039; if you prefer). In my experience when it comes to dietary supplements at least, social workers are all too often still reluctant to allow service users to choose to allow a certain amount of reasonable risk into their lives, seemingly wishing to wrap them up in as much cotton wool as possible. For example, during my fight (and it was a fight) to secure self-directed support for my aunt I was told by a social worker that she would only agree to my aunt being prompted to take her dietary supplements if I could prove that they would &#039;only be good for her&#039;. How could I definitely prove that as many of the things I give my aunt have (due to lack of money) yet to be fully clinically trialed? Surely if my aunt has been deemed to have mental capacity it should be up to her what she would like to be prompted to take when it comes to her medication?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2016 13:47:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Kate Dowling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">148 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-and-risk-enablement#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Pilotlight Action Research</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/pilotlight-action-research</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pilotlight is a co-design project. We are designing together with people who access supports and people who deliver them. We are using the UK Design Council’s ‘Double Diamond’ methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Design Council Double Diamond diagram&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/double_diamond.svg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the ‘Discover’ phase of the first Ageing Well with Self-directed Support pathway, we asked our East Renfrewshire co-design team to do some action research. They were asked to do some interviews to find out what people in East Renfrewshire think about care and support for older people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the co-design team members, M.Steven, has written about the insights she gained from doing this research:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasked by the Pilotlight team to carry out a small survey of East Renfrewshire residents into what they knew about care for the elderly in East Renfrewshire and in particular Self-directed support, I cornered six victims, I mean willing volunteers, at the Kirkton Service in Barrhead and had them complete the Pilotlight questionnaire with me. Of the six, four were carers and two professionals in the social care field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised by the breadth of knowledge displayed by the carer group. While only one had any knowledge of self-directed support (I shall return to this later), what they knew about care for the elderly in East Renfrewshire varied greatly. One knew almost nothing which surprised me considering she was already accessing the Kirkton Service, while two claimed to know very little but in fact knew quite a lot, even citing a befriending service I had never heard of and one was very familiar indeed. As would be expected, the two professionals were well versed on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it came to what the service users wished to see implemented for elderly people in East Renfrewshire and, despite me reminding them that this was a rare opportunity for them to try and steer policy in the area, sadly most of them had very little to say on the matter and more or less said that they were satisfied with what was already available. One though did make a very useful suggestion, that being for the council (or some other body) to set up a one-stop-shop dementia information service (most likely Internet based) where people could go to find information on dementia in general as well as what they should do and what would be available to support them and the person they care for each stage of the disease. Meanwhile, one of the professionals raised the issue of transport in the area citing the need for significant improvements in vital bus routes connecting different parts of East Renfrewshire. To cite just one example, I subsequently learned at the last Pilotlight workshop that there is no direct bus link between Barrhead and Giffnock, which I find extraordinary!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turning to the crux of the matter - what the group knew about self-directed support. Again, the respondents varied greatly in their awareness. All but one of the carer cohort knew absolutely nothing about it, while the one who was familiar with it knew a lot. When I asked her how and when she had learnt about SDS she replied that it was through a talk given at a carers’ centre by a member of the East Renfrewshire Self-directed Support Forum (I learnt at the last Pilotlight workshop, that the speaker was Rosalina Rowan).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 16:46:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">144 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/pilotlight-action-research#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
