<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - co-design</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/tags/co-design</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Achieving Successful Co-design</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/achieving-successful-co-design</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Achieving Successful Co-design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;People entering into a co-design process need to be there in good faith with the potential to influence change. If they are practitioners, they need buy-in at an organisational level about their input in the co-design group and what they can bring back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value everyone equally. Lived experience is as valuable as professional experience. We do this by offering to pay people who do not earn a salary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pay careful attention to the practical arrangements to ensure everyone can participate – we have developed an &lt;a href=&quot;/co-design/tools/inclusion-form&quot;&gt;Inclusion Form&lt;/a&gt; to make sure we identify and respond to everyone’s needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break down ‘them’ and ‘us’ barriers whenever possible. Mix people up. Move away from ‘roles’ and instead focus on skill sets and ‘what we’re good at’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a working together agreement as a group. Ask people what their hopes are for the project and what their concerns are. As a group think about how you can overcome concerns and achieve the hopes together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use tools to help everyone have a voice e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/co-design/tools/stop-and-i-want-speak-cards&quot;&gt;Stop, ‘I want to speak’ talking cards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid buzzwords and jargon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give people responsibilities e.g. homework to complete beforehand. This will help those who perhaps don’t speak up in the group have their voice heard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be transparent about where you are in the design process. Make people feel comfortable when they are in the messy, idea generation, stages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give people the opportunity to complain (within reason!), listen to the complaints and write them down. If they have ideas about changing the process, facilitate these where possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 14:46:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">200 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/achieving-successful-co-design#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
