<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - Carmen Gillies</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/authors/carmen-gillies</link>
 <description>Development Officer Social &amp; Micro Enterprise, Moray Council
</description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>How role plays have helped us design support for people setting up small businesses using SDS</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/how-role-plays-have-helped-us-design-support-people-setting-small-businesses-using-sds</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Hairdressing role play in action&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-web-3x2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/styles/web_3x2/public/media/PL2-Sally-hairdressing.jpg?itok=E3vp0lwC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to truly explore and understand how the people around you are living their lives and the issues they may face on a day to day basis, leads to one answer. The best way to experience this is through stepping into their shoes. This is what we did as part of the IRISS Pilotlight pathway workshop. Throughout the recent workshops we have developed characters to facilitate with scenario based situations. This was identified as a crucial design tool in order to explain a situation based on a fictitious character which people from all areas of life could relate to. Through developing a fictitious character and acting out a scene from a fictitious but realistic world, the results of role play offered a very amusing session but also extremely informative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the surface, role play offered hilarity and joviality between those acting out their parts of the play and between the audiences watching. This has created a platform for interaction, as people are more willing to socialise with one another as the role play sparked exciting conversations and bonding between the groups. The deeper and more meaningful results which I believe can assist with supporting people to set up small businesses was from viewing the similarities in the 4 different role plays, which were all created independently but all shared common themes.&lt;br /&gt;
	These common themes were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The involvement and support from your social worker is essential at the start of the business idea. Having your social worker understand why and how you would like to do this is important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surrounding networks of family and friends are essential to support you with the business and to assist with emotional and practical support and help when needed. Having a backup plan is essential.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a visual plan for all to see and understand the journey of your life, including your business plan. If you can see where you are on a plan, you will be able to deal with emotions and expectations more readily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Networking and exploring what is happening in your surrounding area. Either by doing this yourself through reading newspapers, visiting local events or by assigning someone to do this for you e.g. a family member, friend etc. This is known as market research which is crucial in creating a sustainable small business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through identifying these common themes, this cements the important issues which we must not overlook or skim past, when trying to help individuals set up and establish a successful small business. Nevertheless, most importantly, we must always remember the importance of a balanced life style, through realistic goals and expectations with regards to business development and a healthy and fulfilled life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2014 12:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">123 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/how-role-plays-have-helped-us-design-support-people-setting-small-businesses-using-sds#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>How using creative tools like Six Hat Thinking and ‘Pilotlight characters’ are helping us design support for people setting up small businesses using SDS</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/how-using-creative-tools-six-hat-thinking-and-pilotlight-characters-are-helping-us-design</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Six hat form being completed by hand&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-web-3x2&quot; data-delta=&quot;1&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/styles/web_3x2/public/media/PL2-six-hats.jpg?itok=zpcRxQez&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRISS have delivered various methods to our group who are focusing on setting up small businesses through the use of Self Directed Support budgets.  Through the use of creative tools, such as the Six Hat Thinking* and imaginative characters, these simple techniques have created results which I believe would not have been discovered through a simple and traditional question and answer process. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So why is it extremely important to use creative tools when thinking about setting up a small business?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New ideas are the lifeblood of every good business, large or small; it’s the idea that drives us forward. Good ideas can start from a seed of inspiration which needs to be planted and grown to produce a successful and sustainable business.  But where do you start? You will hear people from all walks of life tell you; you must have a business plan. This may sound like an incredible task or challenge when setting up a business as most people enjoy the “doing” and shy away from the planning and paperwork process. Therefore through engaging with creative tools like six hat thinking, the challenge of thinking and developing a business plan can be broken down into “bite size” tasks. By joining together people in the most unexpected ways, like six hat thinking, this begins to connect the dots in ways I never though of. A picture bigger than the first seed of thought started to emerge as the creative process allowed and supported those involved to be creative thinkers and  problem solvers.  This was achieved by focusing on six distinct directions of though. This gave a clear and “easy to use” pathway to follow, which can be used on all ages and abilities. The process can be as interactive as required. From wearing coloured hats representing each section, to creating and making the hats to wear. This can be tailored to the specific needs of the group to create a very positive and interactive workshop. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creative process was extremely beneficial, not only in producing a simple business plan though methodically working on the six themes, but it also offered a platform to discover ideas and possible barriers that had never been taken into account. Through the input from all team members, this creative tool allowed the host to identify pros and cons from different vantage points, which is critical when trying to set up a sustainable business. As this is an interactive and creative process, there are no right or wrong answers, just constructive questions which the host could reflect upon in a very positive and safe environment.  The methodology of the six hat thinking has turned what is so often a complicated and difficult journey into an enjoyable and easy to use process as we all head on the journey of creating a successful small business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Carmen Gillies is the Development Officer for Social and Micro Enterprise at Moray Council&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Six_Thinking_Hats&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Six Hat Thinking&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a book by Edward deBono which describes a tool for group discussion involving six coloured hats. It can help groups think differently about complex issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2014 12:33:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">132 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/how-using-creative-tools-six-hat-thinking-and-pilotlight-characters-are-helping-us-design#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
