<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - Stuart Bowie</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/authors/stuart-bowie</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Stigma</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/stigma</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Train window with rain&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/stigma.jpg&quot; width=&quot;2000&quot; height=&quot;1500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people who have never felt the stigma of being looked down upon by society may not get how it works, so big mouth here is going to give you an example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#039;s say my life is a windscreen, I&#039;m going along, quite happy then the government declare a war on drugs and suddenly it starts to rain. The first and biggest drop of rain lands right at the top of the windscreen, this is the MP calling all drug users and dealers the scum of the Earth and telling everyone they need to be protected from us and our ideals. Social stigma is born. This first drop of rain though does not want to stay at the top of the windscreen though so it starts to descend through the raindrops of the higher and middle classes, gaining momentum and support as it goes down through the working class, the wife beater, the shoplifters, the alcoholics, uniting those people used to stigma and derision against the new target for hatred and vilification until it is no longer a few drops of water but a stream flowing down the windscreen and no matter how fast the wipers work they cannot stop all that water. This is what addicts have faced since the early 80&#039;s when a government official declared AIDS to be a disease carried and spread by gay men and intravenous drug users. By mouthing off without knowing the facts these people have made the lives of addicts close to unbearable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will this ever end? The answer to that question I cannot tell you but it is human nature that keeps stigma alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 10:20:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Kate Dowling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/stigma#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Blueprint for a Peer Support Worker</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/blueprint-peer-support-worker</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;People holding hands&quot; style=&quot;line-height: 1.5em;&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;1&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/Peer%20Supporter_0.png&quot; width=&quot;585&quot; height=&quot;585&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the name suggests, the role of a Peer Support Worker is best done by someone with experience in the client’s particular ailment.  Be this addiction, alcoholism or mental illness it is important that the Peer knows what they are talking about and has the empathetic nature to listen to the client.  The Peer must also be approachable, there is no point even going into this line of work if you do not have the people skills to get people to talk to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Peer must also be able to respect the choices the client makes, even if they seem wrong to the Peer at the time, as people only really ever learn from their own experience.  I have already mentioned that a Peer should have good listening skills but they should also have a good memory.  There is nothing more annoying to people than having to repeat the same information time and time again and if this happens the probability of losing the client completely rises significantly.  The Peer must also be friendly but at the same time know when they are getting too involved and be able to back up a little without the client losing all confidence in the worker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good Peer Support Worker will not do the clients work for them but will make the client believe that they can do it and offer praise with each accomplishment along the way.  It is often believed that a Peer Worker should be a role model to their clients and yes, to a point, I agree but a good Peer Worker will see themselves as the lower end of the bar, they have to stay humble and remember who they are and where they have been.  This in turn helps to lessen the chances of the worker relapsing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have left the most important thing in my mind till last.  A good Peer Support Worker has to know when their job is done and their client is ready to move on.  If someone breaks their leg they get a plaster cast and crutches.  When someone is broken inside by one of these illnesses the Peer Worker becomes the crutches.  Their job with the client will not go on forever but leave too soon the client could relapse, stay too long and the client may well become dependent on the Peer.  This I believe is the hardest part of the job of being a Peer Worker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 12:23:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">152 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/blueprint-peer-support-worker#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>SDS vs. SPS</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/sds-vs-sps</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stuart Bowie (SDS for Substance Misuse Recovery co-design team member), through a creative piece of writing, presents his take on self-directed support in relation to addiction. We envisage that it will provoke mixed responses from readers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;people writing together&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/stuart-john-and-yvonne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;2000&quot; height=&quot;1391&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They asked me to think about self directed support and how it could be used,&lt;br /&gt;
	I guess I thought too deeply when I worked out how it could be abused,&lt;br /&gt;
	I&#039;m not saying every addict will, I base this on myself,&lt;br /&gt;
	And nowadays my experience is my only wealth.&lt;br /&gt;
	Take one chaotic user who is due up in court,&lt;br /&gt;
	Add one social worker pushing self directed support,&lt;br /&gt;
	Then take away the number of offences he&#039;s committed before,&lt;br /&gt;
	And before too long you all will come up with the exact same score.&lt;br /&gt;
	The man will tell the social worker that he will pay any fine,&lt;br /&gt;
	The social worker counters &quot;I&#039;m not falling for that line&quot;,&lt;br /&gt;
	The man then says &quot;Right then tell me just what I&#039;ve got to do&quot;,&lt;br /&gt;
	&quot;To avoid a prison cell and a fucking hairy screw&quot;.&lt;br /&gt;
	&quot;You&#039;ve got to give up drugs&quot; she&#039;ll say, &quot;And this may well help you&quot;,&lt;br /&gt;
	&quot;A fund for all the help you need, enough to help you through&quot;,&lt;br /&gt;
	The addicts eyes do twinkle as he sees another scam,&lt;br /&gt;
	Like when he got the money for a brand new baby&#039;s pram.&lt;br /&gt;
	That time he went on ebay and got one for half price,&lt;br /&gt;
	And another couple of hundred would sort him out quite nice,&lt;br /&gt;
	So he&#039;ll say with so much feeling &quot;Yes, I really want to change&quot;,&lt;br /&gt;
	&quot;If you could sort that money out?&quot;, &quot;I&#039;ll see what I can arrange&quot;,&lt;br /&gt;
	You see we junkies are not fools and we can damn well act,&lt;br /&gt;
	And to get our next score with the Devil we would make a pact,&lt;br /&gt;
	You&#039;re quite mistaken over who to help and why,&lt;br /&gt;
	So save your cash and give it to the next Big Issue guy.&lt;br /&gt;
	I expect a mixed reaction to this one but this giving Self Directed support to people in Chaotic addiction is rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 17:29:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Kate Dowling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/sds-vs-sps#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Self-directed Support for Substance Misuse Recovery : The Barriers and Opportunities</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-substance-misuse-recovery-barriers-and-opportunities</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;The Four Self-directed Support Options&quot; title=&quot;The Four Self-directed Support Options&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/SDS_4options.png&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;391&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory self directed support seems to be the ideal step forward for people suffering problems with addiction, alcoholism or depression but like all such schemes it has its failings.  This project seems to be single minded about just who needs help and can access funding through SDS.  If by chance you are not under a social work order and have done the hard graft to make the transition from compulsive addict to person in recovery I am afraid this scheme will not help you.  To be very blunt this initiative is aimed only at the people still in active use with a chaotic lifestyle.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I fully accept that people need help with their problems but if it is the social worker telling them they need to get clean then I will be honest with you, that person is not ready.  A person with addiction issues cannot be told when they have to stop or how they do it.  It has to be the person&#039;s own choice and that person must feel that they made the choice alone, not through the pressure put upon them by a social worker.  Come on folks, the clue is in the name, Self Directed Support!!  It implies that the person must be in the right state of mind to make these choices and understand and want the various forms of support available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#039;ll grant you that on paper this initiative sounds wonderful.  It awards those deemed in need with a pot of money that they can spend on a variety of treatments and recovery aids.  This money can either be held by the local council and distributed as the client wishes (within reason) or be given directly to the client to spend as they see fit.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my main worries with this is simply that if you are going to give someone in the early stages of recovery a lump sum of money you are practically inviting them to relapse and if that did happen the client involved would beat themselves up so badly over it most would never look to the scheme again for help even when they were ready to restart their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I guess what I am saying is that if you are serious about this initiative it has got to be opened up to people further along in their recovery and that referrals be accepted from other agencies as well.  Let&#039;s face it, if you have an addict with a criminal record the last person they are going to open up to is their social worker.  Social workers are the people the court get to write the reports on them that can put them in jail.  I have been there and done it.  So please for once listen to someone who knows what they are talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2015 09:31:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">146 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-substance-misuse-recovery-barriers-and-opportunities#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
