<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - Lorraine Greig</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/authors/lorraine-greig</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Pilotlight and Self-directed Support for Substance Misuse Recovery</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/pilotlight-and-self-directed-support-substance-misuse-recovery</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Andrea and Lorraine&quot; title=&quot;Andrea and Lorraine&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/andrea-and-lorraine.jpg&quot; width=&quot;2000&quot; height=&quot;1500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My overall experiences in taking part in the Pilotlight self-directed support workshops over the last 8 months for substance misuse recovery was that I thoroughly enjoyed taking part and meeting all the people from different agencies and, of course, not forgetting the peers in the group who were also in recovery from addictions.  I enjoyed learning about self-directed support and, of course, using the test budget!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt really inspired by the people who attended the workshops and the people giving their stories about being a peer worker. I gained so much knowledge and understanding about self-directed support and peer support through listening to everyone. I learned about all the different agencies that are there to help people with addictions and also for people in recovery, some of whom I never knew anything about so it was really good to gain knowledge about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-directed support is a way in which we saw helped people in recovery get back into a different way of life to which they had been living and self-directed support was put in place to help get the support needed to  meet social needs as well as training  and to help support the move in to employment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the discussions that we had about different topics and of course the little disagreements because everyone had their own opinion!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own test budget was used to help me gain my driving license which would help me a great deal. I am still in the process of doing my theory which is on the last day of the work shops 23rd of June after we finish at 5.30pm. I have failed my theory test twice and I think that if I didn&#039;t have the encouragement of everyone at the workshops I would have gave up by now, but its going to be third time lucky I hope and then my intense driving course will be done and hopefully I will be driving soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Update - I passed!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The part of Pilotlight that interested me a lot was the fact that Turning Point Scotland were employing two peer workers for self-directed support. Although the positions are only for a year I am really interested and excited about the opportunity for two of the people that have been attending the workshops, to gain employment with Turning Point Scotland. I would love the opportunity to gain more knowledge and hopefully be appointed for one of the jobs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have learned about the ten recovery outcomes and all the skills needed to become a peer worker for substance misuse. From reviewing the job description for the position I firmly believe I have the potential required to  meet the criteria effectively for this position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to encourage others by letting them know that you have been through the same as them and that there&#039;s light at the end of the tunnel. This allows us to relate to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judith and Kate really inspired and encouraged me and I learned so much from them as I did from everyone else that took part in the workshops. I think that self-directed support is real way of encouraging and helping people to achieve and get things they need to support with their journey in recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 10:42:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">171 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/pilotlight-and-self-directed-support-substance-misuse-recovery#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Self-directed Support Peer Support Workers: What should the employee and employer expect of each other?</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-peer-support-workers-what-should-employee-and-employer-expect-each-othe-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Person with bag&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-default&quot; data-delta=&quot;2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/media/peer-worker.jpg&quot; width=&quot;2000&quot; height=&quot;1333&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the expectations of an employer from a peer worker in Self-directed Support?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An employer would expect the peer worker to have a good knowledge and understanding of Self-directed Support. An employer would expect to treat any peer worker the same as any other worker thus having appraisals and staff meetings regularly. They would expect a peer worker to have good timekeeping skills and to be flexible. They would expect the peer worker to have been free from illicit substances for 2 years and be a champion in recovery. The potential employee would have to fit the criteria asked for in the job advertisement such as being able to give examples of what their SDS was used for and how it helped make a difference in their life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An employer will ask the peer worker to demonstrate a positive attitude and contribute to the job. Reliability is a must in this position as it shows the person who they are supporting that they are dedicated. Empathy and treating the person they are supporting with respect would be equally important as would showing confidentiality. The employer would also expect the peer worker to be able to learn new things and ways that would help the person whom they are supporting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An employer would expect a peer worker to do on going training and to be able to share their lived experiences to enhance and help the others taking part in the training. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A peer worker would have to be truthful about their recovery and be able to show skills and all the values needed for the position including boundaries and how to keep themselves safe. An employer would also expect the peer worker to be able to be strong enough to be around people who are still using illicit substances and recognise boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the expectations of a peer worker from an employer?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A SDS peer worker would expect their employer to treat them with respect and like any other member of their staff. They would expect to receive ongoing training and be kept up to date with any changes. A peer worker would expect to be given an induction and a list of the codes and practices for the company. An employer should be able to provide team building exercises and interact so that a peer worker can get to know other members of staff and build up a good relationship with them. Employers should be able to give the peer worker regular supervision and have “an open door&quot; policy so they feel that they can approach management if they have any issues. A peer worker would expect their employer to discuss and make them aware of any differences and changes relating to Self-directed Support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A peer worker should be able to know a bit about the background of a person whom they are supporting therefore a supervisor or manager should provide relevant information. An employer should train the peer worker on the protocol on when someone they are supporting displays dangerous or exploitative behaviour. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employers should be willing to listen and advise the peer worker on situations as they arise. Employers should also encourage the peer workers and use them as “Experts by Experience” in training with non peer workers therefore giving the best chance of peer support benefiting the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 15:04:40 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Kate Dowling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-peer-support-workers-what-should-employee-and-employer-expect-each-othe-0#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Peer Support : Values and Skills for Self-directed Support</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/peer-support-values-and-skills-self-directed-support</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Peer support was recognised first in the 18th century by Pussin and Pinel in France and has emerged throughout periods of psychiatry.  The mental health service has used peer support since the early 1990’s and over the last 20 years it has been used more and more to help people in their recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The requirements for this position as a peer support worker for self-directed support would be to have a good knowledge of what self-directed support is all about and who is entitled to it. Having knowledge and a clear view of what’s involved in being a peer support worker would have to be a must for this position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy and compassion are values that would be required and they would help lead to a mutually empowering relationship. Shared personal experiences of recovery and how self-directed support made a difference to make life easier and help recovery. Experiences of how self-directed support helped in recovery would help inspire and promote self-directed support. Helping people decide what kind of things they would use self-directed support for and how it might change their life for the better but also realising people’s capabilities and expectations, and not going over that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are likely to face challenges and should be prepared for set backs but all this will help the peer support worker grow and learn from the experience. Mutual honesty is a needed value in peer support. As a peer support worker for self-directed support you would have to treat people with respect and of course, confidentiality is a skill you would have to demonstrate. Working in peer support, knowing your boundaries, avoiding being judgmental and promoting recovery but accepting people for where they are on their own recovery path is an essential skill you would need to know and demonstrate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encouraging peers to engage with different services, helping build social supports and making community connections that would make a difference and help with their recovery is a value needed for this position. Peer support in self-directed support will be demanding work, flexibility is needed and to be a role model in recovery is important in this role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is thought that peer workers are more gentle, honest and more humane because they have lived experience of how people feel regarding the situation that they are in and also the stigma and relationships that are associated with substance misuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2016 09:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Judith Midgley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/peer-support-values-and-skills-self-directed-support#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
