<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - Katrina Watson</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/authors/katrina-watson</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>The potential SDS offers people who want to set up their own small business</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/potential-sds-offers-people-who-want-set-their-own-small-business</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Six Hats form being filled by hand&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-web-3x2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/styles/web_3x2/public/media/PL2-6-hats_0.jpg?itok=06gQbZ4R&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our third Pilotlight pathway we are working with a co-design team of people who deliver and access support in Moray to look at how self-directed support can be used for small business development. In this blog post, Katrina Watson, one of the team members, writes about what she thinks self-directed support can offer people who want to set up a small business. Here&#039;s what she has to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-directed support could hugely help people starting their own business as there are many people like myself on benefits that have skills that could &amp;amp; can be used to take their life forward &amp;amp; upwards. They could move from being isolated, sitting at home not knowing what their future holds, with feelings of loneliness &amp;amp; emptiness. Not wanting to be a statistic on a government list or being seen as a lazy layabout sitting about the place “bleeding the state dry and pushing up taxes”. A few people may feel this is an easy, okay way to live their lives but there are many more that want to put their bit back into society. As well as to lift their lives, confidence and well being. They have a healthy work ethic that they want to pass on to their children &amp;amp; to provide for those children. To also give themselves &amp;amp; their families a better quality off life. Feeling that there is a future out there somewhere where they are a valued and productive member of society where these feeling may not previously have existed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-directed support could be a very positive experience for them to fulfil their true potential to whatever level that is. It could be making jam/chutneys, home baking to sell in local shops and/or café’s. Making arts &amp;amp; crafts to sell at craft fairs, cleaning windows, cutting grass, DIY or even using previous qualifications and experience to start their own business employing others to help take their business and/or product to a wider field, range of people and places where hopefully these services/products do not already exist. Opening up other avenues to built on and expand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also feel that there needs to be provisions in place to help individuals move forward with their projects. There could be a brochure or pack put together for people to get started with a backup network of people in place to help move forward and to direct them to the appropriate services they may need whether those people help with accounts, tax, or the job centre to find out how this will effect their benefits. These helpers would presumably be the same team of people that would be directing self-directed support for other uses than setting up a small business or micro enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever avenue travelled with your self-directed support it should be one that is beneficial to both the person in receipt of the extra help and those around them. This helps on both a physical, mental &amp;amp; emotional level for both the recipient &amp;amp; their family, friends &amp;amp; support network. Life can be hard at the best of times, lifting it at the bad times has got to be a step forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 11:36:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">119 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/potential-sds-offers-people-who-want-set-their-own-small-business#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>My experiences of the co-design group</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/my-experiences-co-design-group</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Group working&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-web-3x2&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/styles/web_3x2/public/media/PL2-DSC_0006.jpg?itok=Liep3bng&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was unsure of coming along to the group initially as have no previous experience of this kind of thing but thought I would go to the first one or two to see what it was all about. Also I wanted to know more about self-directed support being the nosy kind and felt that if this is going to affect me then I might as well know about it from the start instead of being a straggler for a change. The thought of having some information that others don&#039;t means there will come a time when I can pass information on and make something clearer for them. It will also help me as I&#039;m generally regarded as a thicko which will come as a nice surprise to most, nice to be clued up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did like the idea of making some kind of contribution to the way something might work even if that was in a little way, for example, one of the “workers” picking up on something I say, even as a fly-away comment, taking it back to their place of work and possibly expanding on it. That something that I thought of as a small inept idea being snowballed and expanded upon. Making someone, even one person, see things more clearly. Hopefully, the possibility of seeing something like self-directed support as something that could work for them. There’s nothing worse in life than feeling lost and inept in your own life and/or body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making things clear for people on whatever level, on whatever subject has to be a step forward whether that is self-directed support or any other Government initiative that they might come up with, whether that is now or in the future. I hope my participation in this group will achieve something, even in a minute way. I would like to hope that if there was either a follow up group or another similar group I would be eligible to participate, even with my skewed view of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also feel that this group has given me a boost to my confidence. For me to go and do further subjects whether that is at college, night classes or possibly some charity work to fill both my time and expand my knowledge on life, the world and those in it and around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel that the group has interacted quite well although there have been times when there has been the odd stumble but that I feel is what happens when there are different personalities in one place with varying thoughts, views and opinions.  Also, there is a mix of different service providers trying to protect their area of experience and also clients from yet another different background. Finding the right place for us I feel has helped too (we have moved our workshops to the local football club venue). It is a better mix of services / space for this particular enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-field-photo-credit field--type-text field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;* Photography by Margaret Adams, member of Moray co-design team.&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2013 12:15:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">128 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/my-experiences-co-design-group#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
