<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Pilotlight - Self-directed support - Margaret Adams</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/category/authors/margaret-adams</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>SDS Design for People with Fluctuating Conditions – A Carer’s Perspective</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/sds-design-people-fluctuating-conditions-carers-perspective</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;a scenario&quot; style=&quot;width: 1024px; height: 685px;&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-web-3x2&quot; data-delta=&quot;1&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/styles/web_3x2/public/media/PL2-DSC_0018.jpg?itok=Wp5hqA0t&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-directed support, with careful planning, could be a great help to the well-being of people with fluctuating mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The planning and form filling parts of the assessment should always be done when the person concerned is in a “well and positive mode”. Who does the assessment with the person concerned is also very important. It must always be done by a worker with mental health training, preferably by someone already known and trusted. A worker not familiar with the mental health history of the person might think that in a “well period” the person does not seem to be in need of extra help. A worker known to the person knows the need to keep them on a stable pathway and also the psychological behaviour of the person when they are unwell. Discussions with the person when they are well enables the best plans for their continual well-being and addresses making a plan for when they are unwell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is the nature of some mental health illnesses that the person does not always know when they have crossed over the line from being well to being unwell, this would be especially important if the person was in charge of their own budget. A third party may need to be involved to judge the state of mental health enabling the person to make their own decisions or at what point a third designated party take over such decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these plans are made with a lot of forethought it could be very beneficial to the client. I feel it needs three main points of planning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planning for Wellness&lt;/strong&gt; – and attaining achievable outcomes for the person in times of wellnesss, for example, social activities, group meetings, equipment for the enablement of hobbies (thus helping people to use their time in a productive way). People can expand their talents in crafts, arts etc. that could be focussed towards greater fulfilment with help with basic equipment; courses to enable learning – the choices are endless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height: 1.5em;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planning for unwellness&lt;/strong&gt; – ensuring that the doors that have been opened for the above activities are not closed, and that people know that changes can be made to enable them to get more support, either in day centres, visits within their own homes or in other places that they feel is a safe environment. It is at these times that a third party is needed that the person trusts to either help them or make direct decisions for them, having only their well-being in mind.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height: 1.5em;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re-introduction into wellness&lt;/strong&gt; – and to the activities and plans originally put in place to help continuous well-being. This should be done at an agreed pace of introduction that the person is comfortable with.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Self-directed support I feel will be a perfect pathway for a big percentage of people with mental health problems, enabling them to take charge of their lives in a positive way and at the same time having the safety nets in place at times when they are unable to cope with day to day living with the help of their mental health team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-field-photo-credit field--type-text field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;* Photography by Margaret Adams, member of Moray co-design team.&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2013 12:00:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">122 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/sds-design-people-fluctuating-conditions-carers-perspective#comments</comments>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Self-directed support – overcoming the fears</title>
 <link>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-overcoming-fears</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;
          &lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot; property=&quot;content:encoded&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Group photo&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-web-3x2&quot; data-delta=&quot;1&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/sites/pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/files/styles/web_3x2/public/media/DSC_0043-1.jpg?itok=MHAAo2dY&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last six months I have been attending the Pilotlight workshops in Moray. We have been addressing how best to introduce self-directed support to people with mental health problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a full time carer for a friend who has both physical and mental health problems. Although I could see how people with physical disabilities could benefit from SDS, for example, personal care at times that suits them, respite care in the form of short breaks or disability aids; I could not at first see how people with mental health problems could benefit. One of the main problems that I could foresee was the inability of some people with mental health problems to take care of their own finances, especially at times when their illness is such that they are unable to make stable decisions for their own personal lives and financial decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we as a group worked through this problem, I see that the four SDS options could allow people to opt in and out. Also, there is a choice of the mix of the first three options and, most importantly, with option three, people can choose to keep things as they are, with the local authority directing their service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fear was that people would be given a sum of money to use and they would have to do and keep accounts themselves. I feel that when introducing people with mental health problems to SDS, the three main things to get over are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;It is not compulsory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;None of the support they have at the moment will be taken from them. Day centres and the support from the mental health team are paramount to the day-to-day wellbeing of the majority of people in need of mental health care. Any threat, whether real or imaginary, to the loss of this support could cause stress and a relapse. This is why it must be stressed that nothing is being taken away from them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That SDS has nothing to do with benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;At our very first meeting there were people from various mental health and council offices, two Pilotlight facilitators, myself and eight people who use mental health services. Because of the above fears, sadly the day divided into a them and us situation and spoiled the first meeting. This was caused I feel because of fear and a feeling that something was being taken away from the mental health users group. I feel that if time on the first meeting was spent explaining just what self directed support was about to the group of mental health service users, a lot of the issues raised at the first meeting would have been avoided. However it is a pilot and a pilot is primarily a learning device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are now six meetings on. We have united greatly as a group and I feel we have begun to find solutions to the many problems that will be found when SDS is introduced to mental health service users, their families and supporters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2013 11:11:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>admin_pilotlight</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">118 at https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk</guid>
 <comments>https://pilotlight.iriss.org.uk/blog/self-directed-support-overcoming-fears#comments</comments>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
